Guide to the James Brownlee Rankin photograph collection: Charles M. Russell circa 1875-1939
Montana Historical Society Research Center
James Brownlee Rankin photograph collection: Charles M. Russell
circa 1875-1939
Montana Historical Society Photograph Archives
Lot 009
Rankin, James Brownlee, 1900-1962
1 box
138 photographic prints and 1 tintype
1 nitrate film negative
3 copy negatives (2 safety and 1 nitrate film)
James Brownlee Rankin, a New York and San Bernardino, California, teacher and historian, collected information concerning Montana artist Charles M. Russell in preparation for writing a Russell biography and an illustrated catalog of his work. The photograph collection includes a few views of Rankin, but primarily consists of photographs of Charles M. Russell, Russell's studio and residences, the Russell family and their friends, and people who knew Russell or collected his work.
James Brownlee Rankin was born January 31, 1900, in Denver, Colorado, the son of Reverend James Doig Rankin and Daisy Meloy Rankin. In his college years, Rankin developed a great love for books. Later he also developed an interest in art, particularly western art. This avocation led him to begin the collection of books illustrated by western artists, notably Charles M. Russell and Frederic Remington.
By 1936 Rankin had developed a very strong interest in the work and life of Charles M. Russell. That summer, he decided to research and write a biography of the artist and produce an illustrated catalog of all of Russell's known works. This was his primary goal and the object of his free time until 1940.
Rankin took ads in national and regional newspapers as well as pertinent magazines. From this, he developed a wide range of contacts that had known Russell, knew of him, or owned works by the Montana artist. He made extensive trips to interview individuals and to catalog Russell's art.
Rankin moved to Pasadena, California, in 1939, to be closer to his father and to pursue his teaching and research interests. He married Josephine Crenshaw of New York City in 1940. He never lost his lifelong interest in Russell, but did not continue working on the biography/catalog after that year.
Ultimately he destroyed his manuscript after the publication of a Russell biography by a friend, who Rankin believed, had plagiarized much of his earlier work. The one piece Rankin did publish on Russell was a bibliography of published works illustrated by the artist which appeared in American Book Illustrations in 1938. James Brownlee Rankin died at San Bernardino, California, August 2, 1962.
Charles Marion Russell was born March 19, 1864, in St. Louis, Missouri, to Mary Elizabeth Mead (daughter of Edward Mead) and Charles Silas Russell. He had one sister, Susan Mead Russell (who married T.G. Portis) and brothers: Silas Bent, Edward, Guy, and Wolfert. Silas Bent Russell had a son and daughter, Austin and Isabel. Florence M.N. Russell was Charles M. Russell's stepmother.
At the age of sixteen, Russell’s parents sent him to Montana under the guardianship of a sheepherder from who he soon parted. Working for some time as a cowboy in the West, he continued to sketch, spending his summers on the open range and his winters in various frontier towns, where he often painted pictures in exchange for food or lodging. He sent the original of "Last of the 5000" to Louis Stadler of the Stadler and Kaufman partnership.
In 1896 Russell married Nancy Cooper in Ben Roberts' home at Cascade, Montana. Under her influence and direction he developed from an itinerant cowboy into an artist who painted pictures for a living. The Russell’s adopted a son, Jack Cooper Russell.
By 1920 Russell had achieved financial success and made frequent trips to New York, where he painted for such patrons as Malcomb MacKay and Phillip G. Cole. Russell seldom used models for his paintings or sculpture and took pride in the accuracy of his memory for the details depicted in his scenes of cowboy and Indian life in the West.
For more than a quarter of a century Russell produced works depicting the West as he had known it before the advent of barbed wire, the automobile, etc. He maintained a studio in Great Falls, Montana, and for a brief period in Pasadena, California. Charles M. Russell died October 24, 1926.
James W. Bollinger, William S. Hart, Harry Stanford, and Phil Weinard were among the collectors of works by Russell.
The photographs in the James Brownlee Rankin photograph collection: Charles M. Russell span the years 1875-1939. The collection contains a few photographs of James Rankin, but the majority of the photographs are images of Charles M. Russell, Russell's family and friends, Russell's residences and studio, and people who knew Russell or collected his work. There are a few photographs of Russell's Native American friends and the Russells and their friends dressed in Indian costumes, and of the hearse at Russell's funeral. The collection contains 138 photographic prints arranged by subject.
Many of the photographs in this collection are attributed to specific photographers or photographic studios and lists of these photographers and/or studios follow. However, numerous photographs are unattributed and are not listed.
Photographs in the collection are the work of the following Montana photographers:
H.C. Eklund Studio, Great Falls and Fort Benton (3 photographs)
Leslie Lyle, Helena (1 photograph)
Pearl Thompson, Great Falls (1 photograph)
Thiri Aerial View Service (T.A.V.S.), Polson (1 photograph)
Yaw Photo Shop, Great Falls (3 photographs)
Photographs in the collection are the work of the following non-Montana photographers:
A.J. Fox, St. Louis (1 photograph)
Free Studio, Davenport, Iowa (1 photograph)
Gilbert and Bacon, Philadelphia (1 photograph)
Habenicht (1 photograph)
T.L. Rivers, St. Louis (1 photograph)
Scholten, St Louis, Missouri (1 photograph)
The photographs are arranged by subject and organized into the following 18 subject-based series: Series I. Rankin Family, Series II. Russell Family, Series III. Russell Family Residences, Series IV. Russell Studios, Series V. Mead Family, Series VI. Portis Family, Series VII. Art, Series VIII. Artists, Series IX. Campbell Family, Series X. Cities and Towns, Series XI. David Family, Series XII. Groups, Series XIII. Landscapes, Series XIV. Marchand Family, Series XV. Men, Series XVI. Native Americans, Series XVII. Roundups, and Series XVIII. Women.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
2 duplicates of photographs already cataloged in the Huffman photograph collection were separated from the collection.
See the James Brownlee Rankin research collection: Charles M. Russell, 1910-1962, MC 162. Biographical information was taken from MC 162 biography, biographical reference books, and vertical files.
This collection is indexed under the following headings. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Russell, Charles M. (Charles Marion), 1864-1926.; Russell, Nancy Cooper, -1940.
Russell family.
Art, American -- Montana; Ethnic Costume.; Indians of North America; Women -- Montana.
Great Falls (Mont.)
Kodak card photographs.
Photographic prints.
Fine Arts; Montana; Native Americans; Women
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Rankin Family, Series I
  - James Brownlee Rankin, alone and with unidentified women, undated (Box-folder 1 / 1)
- Russell Family, Series II
  - Charles M. Russell: portraits, undated; wearing Native American dress and holding gun, undated; seated on his horse Monte in front of the Park Hotel, Central Avenue, Great Falls, 1899; in front of his studio, Great Falls, no date; at his mountain lodge, undated; and fishing, undated (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Charles M. Russell: portraits, undated; and view with horse Nena, Great Falls, May, 1913 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Charles M. Russell with Nancy Russell: circular Kodak card photograph of both of them taken circa 1896; horseback riding with Young-Hunter, 1915; seated with pistol and rifle, undated; with Austin and Isabel Russell and CMR and Isabel in Indian costume, circa 1910; with Fergus Mead while painting "In the Wake of the Buffalo Runners," circa 1911; with groups including J.W. Bollinger and the Charles Schlatzlein family at Bull Head Lodge, undated, circa 1910-1911 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Charles M. Russell with others: carte de visite of CMR and Archie Douglas in uniform at Burlington Military School in New Jersey, circa 1878; on horseback with Hank Warehime, Pete Vann, Henry L. Keeton, and Dan Martin, 1883; twirling rope with Albert Trigg in front of log cabin studio, undated; with Phil Weinard in Native American dress, Helena, 1888; with Weinard, Big Belly, and Charlie, Palliser Hotel, Calgary Stampede, 1919 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Charles M. Russell with others: William S. Hart; son Jack Russell; James W. Bollinger and John Lewis, undated (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Charles M. Russell with Bill Rance, undated (Oversized M—1)
  - Charles M. Russell's funeral: horse drawn hearse in front of Great Falls home and studio, 1926 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Florence M.N. Russell (CMR's stepmother): with Marion and Christmas tree, 1939; on the beach, undated; with Helen (in fur coat) and Homer Britzman, and Britzmans' dog in Pasadena, California, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Carte de visite portrait of James Russell (CMR’s paternal grandfather); Mary Elizabeth Mead Russell and Charles Silas Russell (CMR’s mother and father); Edward Russell, Guy Russell and Wolfert Russell (CMR’s siblings), undated (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Nancy Cooper Russell: portrait; and with Louise Fernald, Josephine Trigg, and Jack Russell), undated (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Silas Bent Russell (CMR’s brother); Austin Russell (Silas's son) with Bill Kreighoff sitting in front of fireplace illustrated with CMR's art and autographed screens at Bull Head Lodge, Lake McDonald; and portrait of Silas's his daughter Isabel Russell Wenneis, undated (Box-folder 1 / 11)
- Russell Family Residences, Series III
  - Drawing of Charles S. Russell family residence, Oakhill Farm, 1875; Jake Hoover cabin, undated; Ben Roberts house and C.M. Russell cabin, Cascade, Montana, circa 1937; and gazebo at Bull Head Lodge, Lake MacDonald, no date) (Box-folder 1 / 12)
- Russell Studios, Series IV
  - Charles M. Russell studio, Great Falls: exterior view showing stone wall in front with drawing of buffalo head, undated; and interior view when a museum showing display cases with artifacts, 1937) (Box-folder 1 / 13)
- Mead Family, Series V
  - Portraits of Edward Mead (CMR's maternal grandfather) and his second wife, undated (Box-folder 1 / 14)
- Portis Family, Series VI
  - Susan Mead Russell Portis (CMR’s sister) and her husband, T.G. Portis, undated (Box-folder 1 / 15)
- Art, Series VII
  - Sculptures: Indians and tepee, probably by C.M. Russell; plaster cast of Russell by Jessie Lincoln, selected for American Hall of Fame, undated (Box-folder 1 / 16)
- Artists, Series VIII
  - Erin Hoy standing with his pencil portrait of Charles M. Russell, circa 1939; portrait; and same portrait in the front window of THE MINT bar, Great Falls, circa 1939 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
- Campbell Family, Series IX
  - Mr. and Mrs. Alex Campbell with Mina Mathey, and James B. Rankin, at the Campbell home in Great Falls, Montana, undated (Box-folder 1 / 18)
- Cities and Towns, Series X
  - Great Falls, Montana: public library, undated (Box-folder 1 / 19)
- David Family, Series XI
  - I. Finch David: sitting on bench with an unidentified man (an American flag is reflected in the window behind them), Kendall, MT, undated; standing with unidentified man, July 25, 1937; on horseback, undated; standing beside the grave of his wife, Grace, in Utica cemetery, July 26, 1937; with I.F. David Jr., W.A. Shaules, and automobile, September 6, 1938), 1937-1938 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
- Groups, Series XII
  - Groups - Unidentified: includes people seated on a large rock formation and people standing in front of a house, undated (Box-folder 1 / 21)
- Landscapes, Series XIII
  - Giant Springs and Missouri River near Great Falls, undated (Box-folder 1 / 22)
- Marchand Family, Series XIV
  - John N. Marchand and Mrs. Marchand, wearing cowboy clothes; and posed in artists' studio, undated (Box-folder 1 / 23)
- Men, Series XV
  - Judge James W. Bollinger, undated; Will Crawford, New York illustrator, alone and with J.B. Rankin, undated; Pony Bill Davis, undated; Wallis Huidekoper, owner of American Ranch, Two Dot, MT, undated; Charles M. Joys on horseback, undated; Henry Keeton, undated; Frank B. Linderman and Harry P. Stanford, Kalispell, MT, July 16, 1937; and James W. Masterson, undated (Box-folder 1 / 24)
  - Ben Roberts standing in front of his home and shop in Helena, MT, July 23, 1937; Louis Stadler, Helena, MT, July 23, 1937; F.E. Stranahan, undated; Buck Taylor "King of the Cow-boys", undated; W.C. Tyler, St. Louis, undated; Robert Vaughn wearing buckskin coat and holding a gun, undated; and Phil Weinard dressed as an Indian and in a suit, undated (Box-folder 1 / 25)
  - Men: includes a tintype of unidentified men wearing Indian headdresses and unidentified portraits, undated (Box-folder 1 / 26)
- Native Americans, Series XVI
  - Mo-See-Ma-Ma-Mos (Young Boy), Cree Indian, portraits and standing by C.M. Russell's grave; and portrait of One Bull, Hunkpapa Sioux, undated (Box-folder 1 / 27)
- Roundups, Series XVII
  - Judith Basin roundup crew on horseback, 1883 (Box-folder 1 / 28)
- Women, Series XVIII
  - Cassandra O. Phelps standing next to hollyhocks in front of her cottage, July 26, 1937 (Box-folder 1 / 29)